# Rick Farouni | Curriculum Vitae

Department of Psychology, The Ohio State University

✓ rfarouni@gmail.com • ♦ http://rfarouni.github.io/

I am currently a doctoral candidate in quantitative psychology (statistics applied to the analysis of psychological data) at the Ohio State University. My research is focused on the applications of latent variable modelling and machine learning to behavioral, neuroimaging and bioinformatics data. I hold a master's degree in mathematical statistics and I have a strong background in the natural sciences, multivariate statistics, and scientific computing. I am passionate about the open access movement in education, research, and academia and I am dedicated to rigorous science in the public interest.

## **Education**

### Academic Qualifications.....

The Ohio State University

PhD in Quantitative Psychology

Advisor: Professor Robert Cudeck

Dissertation Topic: 'Deep Latent Generative Models'

The Ohio State University

Master of Science in Statistics [GPA 3.80/4]

The Ohio State University

Master's Degree in Quantitative Psychology

Thesis Project: 'Latent Variable Modelling of Categorical Item Responses in a Hierarchical Bayesian Framework'

The Pennsylvania State University

Bachelor's Degree in Psychology with High Distinction [GPA 3.93/4]

Pennsylvania, USA

2011-2012

Ohio. USA

Ohio, USA

Ohio, USA

2012-2014

2012-2014

2015-Present

# Course Projects....

- Multivariate Statistics (STAT 7560): 'Retinotopic Mapping of the Human Visual Cortex Using Independent Component Analysis'
- Advanced Computational Statistics (STAT 7730): 'Bayesian Analysis of Noisy Images Using Markov Random Fields'
- **Statistical Consulting** (STAT 6750): 'Modelling Categorical Perception of Speech Sounds using Beta Regression'

## **Experience**

## Internship..... The Department of Biomedical Informatics Summer Internship Program (BMI SIP) Research Lab of Professor Ewy Mathé, The Ohio State University 2016 **Project**: Developing an R package and a Shiny app for the analysis of data generated from genome-wide chromatin accessibility assays such as ATAC-seq and DNase-seq with the goal of identifying regulatory elements involved in the cancer epigenetic landscape. Teaching Experience..... **Graduate Teaching Associate** Ohio, USA The Ohio State University 2013-present Teaching Assistant for Psychology 2220: Data Analysis in Psychology **Test Preparation Instructor** Moscow, Russia Instructor of the Graduate Management Admission Test (GMAT) 2009-2012 Teacher of English as a Foreign Language Moscow, Russia Teacher of General and Academic English 2001-2009 Journal Review Service..... **Psychometrika** Ad Hoc Reviewer 2015 **Psychological Methods** Ad Hoc Reviewer 2016 **Conference Presentations Joint Statistical Meetings** Seattle Poster Presentation

2015

Poster Title: Across-Subject Predictive Modeling of fMRI BOLD Responses to Faces using a sparse Bayesian Group Factor Analysis Model

# **Awards and Fellowships**

**Graduate Student Conference Presentation Award** 

The Ohio State University 2015

The Center for Cognitive and Brain Sciences Summer Graduate Fellowship

The Ohio State University 2015

**Project Proposal**: 'Decoding the Pixels of the Face Image from the Voxels of fMRI BOLD Activity Patterns'

#### The Social and Behavioral Sciences Summer Fellowship

The Ohio State University 2014

#### **University Fellowship**

The Ohio State University 2012

## **Technical Skill Set**

#### Statistics and Machine Learning

- **Scientific Programming Languages:** Proficient in and comfortable transitioning between *R*, *Python*, and *Julia* depending on computing goals.
- Deep Learning Frameworks: Experienced in using Tensorflow and MXNet.
- Probabilistic Programming Languages: Proficient in Stan; Familiar with Venture.

#### Computer Science

- **Cluster and High-Performance Computing:** Good knowledge of running neuroimaging and bioinformatics analysis pipelines on the Ohio Supercomputer (uses the Torque scheduling system). Basic familiarity with distributed cluster computing using the Spark platform.
- Web and Software Development Tools: LaTeX, Linux OS, Git, Docker, and Bash. Basic knowledge in website development tools such as HTML, CSS, and Jekyll.

#### Domain Specific Software

- Neuroimaging Analysis Software: Nipype, PyMVPA, FreeSurfer, SPM, FSL, and Pycortex.
- **Bioinformatics Software:** Experienced in analysing functional genomics data using R's Bioconductor set of tools, Bowtie2, MACS2, SAMtools, and bedtools.

## **Publications and Software**

# Journal Papers.....

o Baskin, E., Farouni, R., and Mathe, E. (2016). ALTRE: workflow for defining ALTered Regulatory Elements using chromatin accessibility data. Submitted.

#### Software Development.....

o ALTRE: A Workflow for Identifying ALTered Regulatory Elements using Chromatin Accessibility Data. Github Repo: https://github.com/Mathelab/ALTRE.

#### **Personal Details**

- Country of Previous Residence: Russia (12 years)
- Marital Status: Married
- o Interests and Hobbies: Evolutionary Biology, World Cuisines, Experimental Music
- Languages Spoken: English, Arabic, Russian, Spanish (limited)